<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 version="5.0" xml:id="preface">
<info>
  <?db filename="ch-preface"?>
  <title>Preface</title>
</info>

<para>These stylesheets are the third
iteration of stylesheets for DocBook that I’ve written. I started working on the
<link xlink:href="https://github.com/docbook/xslt10-stylesheets">XSLT 1.0
Stylesheets for DocBook</link> in the 90’s, before XSLT 1.0 was
even a W3C Recommendation. I started working on the
<link xlink:href="https://github.com/docbook/xslt20-stylesheets">XSLT 2.0
Stylesheets for DocBook</link> just around the time when XSLT 2.0 became
a W3C Recommendation. I wrote most of
<citetitle>DocBook xslTNG</citetitle> just a month or so before the third anniversary
of the XSLT 3.0 Recommendation.</para>

<para>Why did it take so long?</para>

  <para>To answer that question, we need to reflect for a moment on XSLT and
    its place in the XML ecosystem. When XSLT arrived on the scene, we
    were near the peak of XML enthusiasm. Not only was XML supported
    everywhere, it was possible to imagine XSLT everywhere as well.
    Certainly, the presence of XSLT in the browser felt significant at
    the time.
  </para>
  <para>The ubiquity of XML and the fact that XSLT was “just an XML
    vocabulary” may have contributed to another significant phenomenon:
    lots of users who did not self identify as programmers were learning
    to use XSLT and doing significant things with it.
  </para>
  <para>There were other tools available for transforming markup at the
    time, and arguably some of them were better than XSLT, but they were
    programming languages and you had to be a programmer to use them.
    They were also mostly commercial applications not widely available
    to casual users.
  </para>
  <para>XSLT was free, it was everywhere, and it was used by everyone, not
    “just” programmers. It was the clear winner than and remains the
    clear winner today in terms of markup transformation.
  </para>
  <para>You could do a lot of things with <xref linkend="XSLT10"/>. You could do a lot more
    things than you might at first even have thought possible. (In fact,
    you could do all things, but the
    Turing complete nature of XSLT isn’t relevant here.) Some very
    common tasks, like grouping, were possible but difficult. Lots of
    very useful things were either not possible or required extensions:
    regular expressions, functions, date and time formatting, creating
    special characters in the output, to name just a few.
  </para>
  <para><xref linkend="XSLT20"/> solved all of these problems (and more). Significantly, I
    think, all of these new features appealed directly to almost all
    users of XSLT 1.0. Everyone had encountered a grouping problem
    (building an index, for example). Everyone had wanted regular
    expression matching or date formatting. Lots of users wanted to
    write more sophisticated predicates (and many were willing to learn
    how to use functions to achieve that result).
  </para>
  <para><xref linkend="XSLT30"/> arguably introduces larger and
  more dramatic features than XSLT 2.0 did. There are a bunch of new
  features designed to enable streaming processing; there are
  significant software engineering improvements: packaging, exception
  handling, and assertions; there are common programming language
  constructs like maps and arrays. There is also a selection of
  features inherited from updates to XPath (new functions, a subset of
  <code>let</code> syntax, and support for higher order
  functions, for example).
  </para>
  <para>What’s curious, I think, is that many of these features are probably
    less immediately appealing to many (most?) current users. XSLT 2.0
    doesn’t feel constraining in the same way that XSLT 1.0 did, and the
    features in XSLT 3.0 don’t immediately and obviously solve problems
    that most users have.
  </para>
  <para>Streaming, for example, is incredibly powerful and it’s an important
    and significant milestone in markup processing. It makes it possible
    to solve whole classes of problems that were previously impossible
    to solve or required enormously expensive hardware. But my laptop
    will quite easily process a book full of complex markup that runs to
    hundreds of pages. I don’t have any problems that require a
    streaming processor.
  </para>
  <para>Likewise, packaging is useful and important. The <emphasis>DocBook
    xslTNG</emphasis> stylesheets should absolutely be a package. But
    that’s not true of a lot of stylesheets. There might be software
    engineering benefit in making a package even for stylesheets that
    you don’t intend to distribute, but that’s more likely to appeal to
    people who think of what they’re doing is programming.
  </para>
  <para>Nevertheless, there are lots of good reasons to use XSLT 3.0 even if
    you are “only” transforming documents and even if you don’t think of
    writing transformations as programming.
  </para>

</preface>
