<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 version="5.0" xml:id="getting">
<info>
  <?db filename="ch01.html"?>
  <title>Getting the stylesheets</title>
</info>

<para>There are three ways to get the stylesheets: you can
<link linkend="get-github">download the latest release</link> from
GitHub, you can <link linkend="get-maven">get them from Maven</link>,
or you can clone
<link xlink:href="https://github.com/docbook/xslTNG">the repository</link>
and  <link linkend="building">build them yourself</link>. We’ll cover
the first two options in this chapter; <xref linkend="building"/> covers
the last option in detail.</para>

<section xml:id="get-github">
<title>Download the latest release</title>

<para>The latest release is always available from the
<link xlink:href="https://github.com/docbook/xslTNG/releases">GitHub
releases page</link>. At the time of publication, the latest release was
version <?DocBook-xslTNG-version?>.</para>

<para>Distributed this way, you’ll get a ZIP file that contains the stylesheets
plus a number of ancillary files and tools. These are mostly covered in
the next chapter <xref linkend="using"/>.</para>

<para>You can unzip the file anywhere that’s convenient: in your home
directory or in a system-wide location.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="get-maven">
<title>Getting the release from Maven</title>

<para>The latest release is always available
<link xlink:href="https://search.maven.org/search?q=org.docbook.docbook-xslTNG">from
Maven</link><footnote><para>With the caveat that it sometimes takes a few
hours for the releases to make their way from the registry onto the website.
If you’re chasing the very latest release and it’s just been published, it
may be available before it appears on the website.</para></footnote>.
</para>

<para>The group, artifact, and version ID for the latest release at
the time of publication is:</para>

<para role="center"
><code>org.docbook:docbook-xslTNG:<?DocBook-xslTNG-version?></code></para>

<para>If you’re comfortable using Maven, I’m going to assume that’s all you
need to know.</para>

<para>The Maven distribution differs from the zip file in a couple of ways:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>It doesn’t bundle any of the dependencies. The
<link linkend="get-github">ZIP file</link> is more akin
to
<link xlink:href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/11947037/what-is-an-uber-jar">an
“uber” or “fat” jar</link>; it includes (some of) the core dependencies so
that it works out-of-the-box. Maven is designed to resolve dependencies,
so that shouldn’t be necessary here.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The Maven jar doesn’t include the Python script or the extra resources
(CSS and JavaScript files) because it doesn’t seem like it would be convenient
to extract them from the Maven jar (which will probably be installed deep in
some repository hierarchy well out of sight). Consequently, you may want to
<link linkend="get-github">download the distribution</link> periodically as well.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

</section>
</chapter>

