<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 version="5.0" xml:id="customization">
<info>
  <?db filename="ch03.html"?>
  <title>Customizing the stylesheets</title>
</info>

<para>In many circumstances, the stylesheets can be used “out of the
box” without any customization. But sometimes you may need to change
the formatting of certain elements. One common reason is to change the
formatting of title pages or navigational features. In other cases, it
may be to support local extensions to DocBook or simply to change the
markup to support a particular use case.</para>

<para>Three approaches are possible, with increasing degrees of
effort: changing stylesheet parameters, creating your own
customization layer, or making broader changes to the stylesheet’s
implementation.</para>

<para>The subject of broader implementation changes is the subject of
<xref linkend="implementation"/>. In this chapter, we’ll look at the
easier options.</para>

<section xml:id="change-params">
<title>Changing stylesheet parameters</title>

<para>The <citetitle>DocBook xslTNG Stylesheets</citetitle> define a
lot of parameters. They are all described in <xref linkend="params"/>.
If the change you want to make has already been parameterized, you may
be able to achieve your goal simply by setting a parameter at runtime.</para>

<para>For example, if you want to change the formatting of dates and times
in <tag>date</tag> elements, you can simply change the <link
xlink:href="p_date-date-format">date and time formatting</link>
parameters. Similarly, if you want to change the numeration style of
ordered lists, you can simply change the <link
linkend="p_orderedlist-item-numeration">ordered list item
numeration</link> parameter.</para>

<para>These changes can be accomplished by simply passing the new
values to the processor, on the command line or in a configuration
file, for example. You do not have to write any XSLT to make these
changes.</para>

<para>Parameter values apply to the entire document processed by the
stylesheets. In some cases, you may wish to change the presentation of
just one or small number of elements. This can often be accomplished
with a <link xlink:href="pi_db">db processing instruction</link> in
the source document itself. These customizations can also be
accomplished without writing any XSLT.</para>

<para>If you want to make a change that isn’t supported by a
parameter, or an ad hoc exception that doesn’t have a supporting
processing instruction, you will have to write a customization layer.
(You are invited to submit an issue with your use case if you think it
would be of general interest.)
</para>

<para>You may also find it convenient to write a customization layer
if you want to change several parameters and you find it inconvenient
to pass them all to the processor on every invocation.
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="layer">
<title>Creating a customization layer</title>

<para>A customization layer is simply an XSLT stylesheet that you
write which extends the DocBook stylesheets. The simplest<footnote><para>Ok,
technically, this stylesheet has a couple of namespace references that aren’t
strictly necessary so it could be a teeny bit simpler, but you’ll need those
declarations (and more!) if you want to do anything useful.</para></footnote> customization
layer is:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"
><xi:include href="examples/custom0.xsl" parse="text"/></programlisting>

<para>This customization doesn’t do anything. But you can, for example, redefine
parameters if you wish:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"
><xi:include href="examples/custom1.xsl" parse="text"/></programlisting>

<para>This will have the effect of running the DocBook stylesheets with those two
parameters set as specified.</para>

<para>If you want to change the HTML output for an element, you can write a template
for that element in your customization layer. Consider this DocBook document:
</para>

<programlisting language="xml"
><xi:include href="examples/sample.xml" parse="text"/></programlisting>

<para>Suppose that you decided you wanted to have the
<tag>productname</tag> element link automatically to the vendor
webpage. One way to do that would be to redefine the template that processes the
<tag>productname</tag> element:</para>

<programlistingco>
<areaspec>
  <area xml:id="ex.xmlns-m" coords="5 52"/>
  <area xml:id="ex.excl-m" coords="8 40"/>
  <area xml:id="ex.m-docbook" coords="21 34"/>
  <area xml:id="ex.cramped" coords="24 1"/>
  <areaset xml:id="ex.next-match">
    <area xml:id="ex.next-match-44" coords="44 26"/>
    <area xml:id="ex.next-match-48" coords="48 28"/>
  </areaset>
</areaspec>
<programlisting language="xml"
><xi:include href="examples/custom2.xsl" parse="text"
             xpointer="line=0,;length=1559"/></programlisting>
</programlistingco>

<calloutlist>
<callout arearefs="ex.xmlns-m">
<para>All of the DocBook elements are processed in the “<mode>m:docbook</mode>” mode.</para>
</callout>
<callout arearefs="ex.excl-m">
<para>Remember to exclude all the namespaces you declare so that they don’t wind up
scattered about in your HTML.</para>
</callout>
<callout arearefs="ex.m-docbook">
<para>I repeat, all of the DocBook elements are processed in the
“<mode>m:docbook</mode>” mode. I expect failure to declare this mode is going to be a common
error.</para>
</callout>
<callout arearefs="ex.cramped">
<para>Yes, this whole listing is rather cramped.
<phrase outputformat="print">I’m trying to make it all narrow
enough to fit in the display without overflowing the margins.
</phrase><phrase outputformat="online">I’m trying to make it all narrow
enough to fit in the display without making horizontal scrolling necessary.</phrase>
</para>
</callout>
<callout arearefs="ex.next-match">
<para>Calling <literal>xsl:next-match</literal> invokes the underlying
processing. The effect of this template is to wrap an HTML
“<code>a</code>” around the default processing for
<tag>productname</tag>.</para>
</callout>
</calloutlist>

<para>It’s worth pointing out that if the tag has an
<att>xlink:href</att> attribute, that will generate an HTML
<code>a</code> as well. A more robust stylesheet would check for that,
but I’m trying to keep the example simple.</para>

</section>
</chapter>
