<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
<info>
  <?db toc="false"?>
   <title>Unit Test: glossary.001</title>
   <editor>
      <personname>
         <firstname>Someone</firstname>
         <surname>Random</surname>
      </personname>
   </editor>
   <subtitle>Wikipedia fruits with pepper</subtitle>
   <releaseinfo>Just some test data</releaseinfo>
   <othercredit><orgname>Wikimedia Commons</orgname></othercredit>
</info>

<chapter>
<title>Fruits and Peppers</title>

<note>
<para>The test harness is configured to run this test with the
<parameter>glossary-collection</parameter> parameter pointing to
<filename>src/test/resources/glosscollection.xml</filename>.</para>
</note>

<para>There's a <tag>firstterm</tag> here:
<firstterm>Apple</firstterm>.</para>

<para>And there's a couple of <tag>glossterm</tag>s here:
<glossterm>Peach</glossterm>, <glossterm>Jackfruit</glossterm>,
and <glossterm>Durian</glossterm> (not in the <xref linkend="glossary"/>).</para>
  
<para>We also have <glossterm>Pepper</glossterm> which has
<emphasis>two</emphasis> entries in the glossary. This is wrong, of
course. The application should complain. (Note that when constructing a glossary
automatically, repeated terms are avoided by only using the first. When the glossary
is constructed by hand, removing duplicates is the author’s resposibility.)</para>
</chapter>

<glossary xml:id="glossary">

<glossdiv>
<title>A</title>

<glossentry xml:id="apple">
  <glossterm>Apple</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>An apple is an edible fruit produced by an apple tree (Malus
    domestica). Apple trees are cultivated worldwide and are the most
    widely grown species in the genus Malus. The tree originated in
    Central Asia, where its wild ancestor, Malus sieversii, is still
    found today. Apples have been grown for thousands of years in Asia
    and Europe and were brought to North America by European
    colonists. Apples have religious and mythological significance in
    many cultures, including Norse, Greek and European Christian
    tradition.</para>
    <glossseealso otherterm="pear">Pear</glossseealso>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry xml:id="apricot">
  <glossterm>Apricot</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>An apricot is a fruit, or the tree that bears the fruit, of
    several species in the genus Prunus.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv>
<title>D</title>

<glossentry xml:id="drupe">
  <glossterm>Drupe</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>In botany, a drupe (or stone fruit) is an indehiscent fruit
    in which an outer fleshy part (exocarp, or skin; and mesocarp, or
    flesh) surrounds a single shell (the pit, stone, or pyrene) of
    hardened endocarp with a seed (kernel) inside. These fruits
    usually develop from a single carpel, and mostly from flowers with
    superior ovaries.</para>
    <glossseealso otherterm="apricot">Apricot</glossseealso>
    <glossseealso otherterm="peach">Peach</glossseealso>
    <glossseealso otherterm="nectarine">Nectarine</glossseealso>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv>
<title>J</title>

<glossentry xml:id="jackfruit">
  <glossterm>Jackfruit</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The jackfruit (Artocarpus heterophyllus), also known as jack
    tree, is a species of tree in the fig, mulberry, and breadfruit
    family (Moraceae). Its origin is in the region between the
    Western Ghats of southern India and the rainforests of
    Malaysia.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv>
<title>N</title>
<glossentry xml:id="nectarine">
  <glossterm>Nectarine</glossterm>
  <glosssee>Peach</glosssee>
</glossentry>
</glossdiv>

<glossdiv>
<title>P</title>

<glossentry xml:id="peach">
  <glossterm>Peach</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The peach (Prunus persica) is a deciduous tree native to the
    region of Northwest China between the Tarim Basin and the north
    slopes of the Kunlun Mountains, where it was first domesticated
    and cultivated. It bears an edible juicy fruit called a peach
    or a nectarine.</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>

<glossentry xml:id="pear">
  <glossterm>Pear</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>The pear tree and shrub are a species of genus
    Pyrus, in the family Rosaceae, bearing the pomaceous
    fruit of the same name. Several species of pear are valued for
    their edible fruit and juices while others are cultivated as
    trees.</para>
    <glossseealso otherterm="apple">Apples</glossseealso>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>
  
<glossentry>
  <glossterm>Pepper</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
    <para>Black pepper (Piper nigrum) is a flowering vine in the family Piperaceae, cultivated for
            its fruit (the peppercorn), which is usually dried and used as a spice and seasoning.
            Peppercorns and the ground pepper derived from them may be described simply as pepper,
            or more precisely as <emphasis>black pepper</emphasis> (cooked and dried unripe fruit),
              <emphasis>green pepper</emphasis> (dried unripe fruit), or <emphasis>white pepper
            </emphasis>(ripe fruit seeds).</para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>  
  
<glossentry>
  <glossterm>Pepper</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
        <para>Long pepper (Piper longum), sometimes called Indian long pepper or pippali, is a
          flowering vine in the family Piperaceae, cultivated for its fruit, which is usually
          dried and used as a spice and seasoning. Long pepper has a taste similar to, but sweeter
          and less pungent than, that of its close relative Piper nigrum – from which black, green
          and white pepper are obtained. </para>
  </glossdef>
</glossentry>  
</glossdiv>

</glossary>
</book>
